Friends, if you have taken health insurance
and are planning to get cashless treatment in the future, then
this video is very important for you
because there are some points
which you do not know and when
you go for treatment, your
claim gets rejected there.
I am going to tell you 10 to 11 such points here,
if you follow them then your claim never gets rejected. It is
mostly
seen that your cashless claim gets rejected due to these 10 to 11 reasons,
so please watch the video till the end.
Before moving ahead in the video, let me
introduce myself to you. My name
is Brijendra Gautam and you are watching
ABTech Financial Advisor.
I have been working in the field of insurance and mutual funds for the last three years.
If you have any
query, you can contact us.
If any of your claims is not getting passed,
you can also contact us.
Let's move ahead in the video. First
point: Incorrect information on the form.
Like, for cashless treatment  When you go
to the hospital, first of all you have to
fill the pre-authorization form.
In this you have to fill the policy details,
patient details, patient's
name, date of birth, address, relation, in
whose name your policy is, you have to fill all the details. So
if you make any
mistake in filling these details,
like there is an in-house claim settlement team from the side of TPA, from
their side your
form goes to the health insurance company,
due to mismatch there your form gets rejected in the first step itself. So
whenever you
fill the entire Thoran form, then fill it after looking at it carefully and
thinking carefully. Second,
whenever you get cashless treatment
done at a non-network hospital, then here you must ensure
that the hospital where you are getting the treatment done is
in the network list of the company. If you go to any non-network
hospital for treatment, then
your claim will be rejected in cashless,
although later
you can go for reimbursement, so how will you know whether
a particular hospital
is non-network or in the network?
Whichever company has your health insurance,
go to the health insurance company's website or app, you will
get the complete list of network hospitals there, after looking at that list
you should search for the hospital and only then
go for cashless treatment, otherwise
you will not get cashless treatment or cashless
claim. Thirdly, blacklisted
hospital: All insurance companies have some blacklisted
hospitals too, if you get
treatment done at such a hospital, then
neither will you be able to get cashless treatment
nor will you get your claim in return. So,
you can check the blacklisted hospitals by going to the insurance company's website
which
companies have blacklisted hospitals,
you should not go to those blacklisted hospitals at all,
otherwise you will
not get any claim there and this
list of blacklisted hospitals keeps changing,
so do not think that the
list which was there 2 years ago will still be there, it keeps changing, so
whenever you go for cashless treatment
or any treatment, you
must first check the list of blacklisted hospitals.
Fourth, non  Disclosure of any
illness: Many times it happens that when you
take a policy, you do not tell about your pre-existing
disease, you do
not share it with the insurance company, you do
not disclose it, so when
in future you
go for treatment and the company comes to know that it is
some disease which you already had, then in such a situation, if the
company comes to know about it, your claim will be
rejected and you will
not get a cashless claim for it. However,
you can apply for reimbursements later, then the
company will investigate it and whatever your valid
documents are, whatever investigations are, you will
prove them, then later you can get a
claim for reimbursements. Fifth,
hospitalization not justified, friends, this is
one such reason due to which most of the
cashless claims are rejected. Now
what happens in this, suppose you have some problem,
you get hospitalized, you get admitted there, you undergo a
lot of tests there, you were kept
admitted for two-three days, but later it is found
that you do not have any disease,
no result came out there.  In a diagnosis
and you return home, in such a situation, you have
definitely been hospitalized, but no
treatment was provided there; only
diagnosis and evaluation took place.
In such a situation, you will not get a cashless claim.
However, you
can later go to reimbursement and claim from there,
and many people do get such claims.
Six specific exclusions: There are
some diseases which
come under a specific waiting period, such as
hernia, stone, cataract, knee replacement. The
waiting
period for these is usually 2 years.
If you are going for treatment for such a disease
and your 2 years have not been completed, then
you will
not get its treatment through cashless treatment, nor will you get its
treatment through reimbursement. So,
whenever you go for any treatment, whether
cashless or rebus, you
must ensure that
you clear the waiting period mentioned in your policy or that the waiting
period has ended.  Only then will you
get a claim, so
definitely keep in mind the waiting period. Let me tell you here
that the normal waiting period is
30 days, the specific waiting
period is 2 years,
apart from this, there is a waiting period of PD i.e.
pre-registered
company, so you should read your policy document
carefully and only then
go for any treatment. Seventh missing
document on the claim submission: Many times it happens
that we get hospitalized,
our treatment is done there, but
when the final bill goes to the company,
some documents are missing there,
okay, so if any document is missing,
then your claim will not be passed in the case, so
in such a situation, whenever you
process for the claim, then all
your documents should be attached,
all the things which are necessary,
you should submit them, only then your cashless
claim gets approved, if seen, then
all this work is done by the TPA,
you do not have to do anything here,
but many  Sometimes,
some documents are missed by the EPA or the in-house team, due to
which your claim gets
rejected, but later
this claim is also approved through a rescinded comment.
Address change: Friends, this also happens with some people
that when they
took the policy, they lived in a Zone B or Zone C city,
but later they shifted
and started living in a Zone 1 city
and at the same time their claim came, but they did
not inform the company that their address has changed
and went there for a cashless claim.
When the company sees that when you
took the policy, you paid the premium in Zone 2 or
Zone 3, and now when
you are giving the Aadhar card document,
you are going to Zone 1 for treatment, you are giving the
Aadhar card of Zone 1 or whatever
Zone 1 address you are giving,
your claim gets rejected here also. One thing I
would like to tell you here is that if you live in the same zone
where you were living at the time of taking the policy, let's say
you have taken the policy in Zone B
and are getting treatment in Zone B only.
Or if you are getting treatment in Zone 1, then there will be no
problem at that time. This
problem arises when you have taken a policy of Zone B
and you shift and start
living permanently in Zone 1 and you have
not informed the company that your address has
changed. So if such an address
change happens to you too, if you used to
live in another city earlier and now you have moved to another city, then
definitely inform the company about it. Ninth
Deductible Friends,
many times the claim is not processed due to this deductible.
Suppose you have taken a policy of Rs 1 crore in
which your base cover is Rs 5 lakh
and super top up is Rs 95 lakh.
Now when you get treatment there, your
bill comes above Rs 5 lakh. In that case,
until the insurance company which had given Rs 5 lakh
does not give the claim settlement letter,
your super top up claim will
not be passed. In such a situation also your
claim will be rejected. To
avoid such a situation, first of all you should keep in mind
that whenever you take super top up  So try to
get both the top-up and base plan from the same company, you will not face any such problem.
10th Lapse Health Insurance: Many
times it happens friends that we do
not get our policy renewed on time
and the date has expired, the grace
period has also ended and at the same time a
claim comes to you, then your policy has lapsed,
then if you go for the claim
in cashless, then you will
not get your claim at all, if your policy has
lapsed, then you will
not get the claim even in terms of terms, so always keep this in mind,
whenever your renewal date is, get it
renewed before that date so that
you do not face any such problem in the future, so
friends, these were the top 10 reasons due to which
most of the people's cashless claim gets
rejected, I hope that
you liked the video which I gave information,
if there is any other point in your knowledge due to which
your claim got rejected, then
you must tell in the comment box so
that other people can benefit and at the
end of the video I would like to say this much, if you  If you have
not subscribed to our channel, then
subscribe to the channel, like and
share the video. If you have any query related to health insurance,
you
can contact us. That's all in this video,
thank you.